Guide to the Albert F.W. Schmidt manuscripts, 1644-1997 MS2199
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Albert F.W. Schmidt manuscripts
1644-1997
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2199
2 Linear Feet
This French manuscript collection contains correspondence, legal documents, pamphlets, notes, and an envelope. The materials date from 1644-1997. Topics include the French Revolution, royal marriages, taxation, and land sales. Ray Rackley, a Gelman Library supporter, partially translated, identified and dated these manuscripts in 1997. He included a written synopsis of the manuscript within each folder. His translations notes are included in the collection.
Box 2
Box 1
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Between 1978-9, Schmidt's daughter, Martha Schmidt, donated portions of her father's private collection of manuscripts and rare books to the Special Collection's Department at George Washington University.
Historical or Biographical Note
Alfred F.W. Schmidt, a former professor of classical and Germanic languages, was the George Washington University Librarian from 1906-33 and the director of the Library School at George Washington (no longer in existence) from 1928-38.
Collection Scope and Content
This French manuscript collection contains correspondence, legal documents, pamphlets, notes, and an envelope. The materials date from 1644-1997. Topics include the French Revolution, royal marriages, taxation, and land sales. Ray Rackley, a Gelman Library supporter, partially translated, identified and dated these manuscripts in 1997. He included a written synopsis of the manuscript within each folder. His translations notes are included in the collection.
Please note: the material listed in this guide is processed and available for use, but there remains unprocessed portions in this collection. These unprocessed documents are in boxes 1 and 2. The unprocessed manuscripts are in one of the following languages: Italian, Spanish, or Latin. There are eight manuscripts in undetermined languages. Use of these manuscripts requires conservation and translation work. See staff for assistance.
Land titles; Taxation; French Revolution.; Marriage; France -- History -- 18th century; France -- History -- 17th century; France; Schmidt, A. F. W. (Alfred Francis William)
- Copy of the Letter that the Catholic King [Philippe V] wrote to King Louis XV., 1722 ca. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  General note
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 02 "King Philippe V of Spain offers his daughter, the Infanta, in marriage to King Louis XV, and proposes to send her to France 'to be brought up and formed in principles suited to the status to which she will be called'" Excerpt from Preliminary description by Ray Rackley. For complete record, see folder.
- New title to land/property inherited by Cyprien and Madeleine Daniel, 01/30/1738 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 03 "Document recognizes that Cyprien and Madeleine Daniel have inherited the described property, including goods, furniture and livestock, at Ermont, in the Duchy and Peerage of Anguien, from their parents Ciprien Daniel and Margaritte Couchard, deceased. "
  For a complete description by Ray Rackley's please see folder.
- Printed copy in French of document issued in the name of Louis XIV, King of France, 05/20/1645 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document .05 See description in folder for further details.
- Baranger, Administrator of the Departement de Maine Letter from the administrative commission of the civic hospices near La Place Maurice, 1797 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 10 See description in folder for further details.
- "Compte que rendent Arnaud de Trilhe, dit Fanget, et Pierre de Troquet, jurats de la ville d'Espsey, 1717-1718" ["Financial accounting given by two Jurats (sworn municipal officers) of the city of Espsey, southern France, for the years 1717-1718."], 1717 ca. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 11 Financial accounting of the town of Espsey, France. The document lists and totals the receipts and expenditures for the year
  See description in folder for further details.
- In horrendum nefas, perpetratum die 5 mensis Jan. 1757 [On the horrible assassination attempt, of five January 1757]. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 13. Booklet, in Latin and French. "In horrendum nefas, perpetratum die 5 mensis Jan. 1757" "Sur l'horrible attentat, du cing janvier 1757. Traduction du poeme Latin." For more information please see prelimary description in folder.
- Le Paradis Terrestre, Poeme Imite de Milton [The Earthly Paradise, Poem in the style of Milton], 1760 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 14. For further details, see folder.
- Sebastien Bontems et autres au proffit de Monsieur [Claude Charles] Rossignol. [Sebastien Bontems and others to the benefit of Monsieur (Claude Charles Rossignol)]., 07/16/1741 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 15. Rental agreement, handwritten in French, at Auguien, France, 1741.
- [Envelope addressed to] Monsieur Le Marquis D'Eskelbecy, 18th ca. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 16. Handwritten envelope. Sent to: Monsieur Le Marquis D'Eskelbecy, En Son Shateau a Esquelbecy, Pau For further details, see folder.
- Titre nouvel contre Les heritiers de Cyprien Daniel 9 mars 1727. [New (property) title against the inheritors of Cyprien Daniel], 03/09/1727 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 20. Handwritten in cursive French on parchment/vellum. For further description see folder.
- Simon de Goussey, demandeur, et Elaude de la Haye, deffendeur. [Simon de Goussey, plaintif, et Claude de la Haye, defendent], 1655 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Folder previously entitled: Schmidt document 22. Legal document, handwritten in French. For further description see folder.
- Ray Rackley notes, [1/2], 1997 -ca. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Ray Rackley notes, [2/2], 1997 -ca. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Manuscripts (Box 4)
  Use gloves with materials from this box.
- De par le roy: Guillaime Urbain de LaMoignon, Chevallier,...Intendant de justice in la generalite de Bordueax. 25 Juin 1712. [ in the name of the King: Guillaime Urbain, night,...intendant, Cordeaux Region. 25 June 1712.], 06/25/1712 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 01." [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Notice to the citizens and inhabitants of Bordeaux and the surrounding parishes (towns) to pay their taxes for the year 1711 and the October quarter of 1710. Names Sieur Sauber and Sieur Marot as the two cheif tax collectors, and lists the respective parishes (tax collection districts) for which each is responsible."]
- Bulletin de la convetion nationale, seance du 12 Floreal, l'an 3 de la republique une et indivisble. A Paris, de l'imprimerie nationale. [Bulletin of the national convetion, session of 12 Floreal, year 3 of the Reqpublique one and indivisible. Paris, from the national press.], 1795 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 04."
  [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Report by Joseph-Marie Chenier on the status of police in the Republic. Decree by the convention constraining emigres, deportes, royalists, critics of the republic. Text and raification of the peace treaty negotiated in Basle, Switzerland, and at Berlin, by Charles August, Baron de Hardenberg, representing Frederic Guillaume, roi de Prusse and Francois Barthelemy, presenting the republique francaise. 5 April 1795 and 15 April 1795. French troops to evacuate occupied Prussian lands on the right bank of the Rhine, and to retain control of the left bank. Prisoners on both sides to be exchanged."]
- Empire Francais. Arrete du prefet du departement de la Creuse, du 30 Juin 1806. [French Empire. Decree of the prefect of the department of La Creuse, 30 June 1806.], 06/30/1806 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 06."
  [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Decree from the Prefect (Chief administrative officer) of the "department de la Creuse" (in central France), declaring invalid all existing permits to carry guns, and giving procedures, with costs, for acquiring new gun permits."]
- Page of coupons, 1797 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 07."
  [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Printed page of coupons good for 300 francs each as "receipts" for a "forced loan" (tax) of 300 francs to the Republique francais. Originally there were 10 coupons, but 2 have been cut out, and presumably redeemed."]
  For more information see preliminary description with item.
- Ordonnance Rendue par le President du Tribunal Revolutionnaire. Du 24 Pluviose, l'an deux de la republique une et indivisble. [Decree promulaged by the President of the Revolutionary Court. 24 Pluviose, year two of the republique one and indivisble.], 01/1793 -02/1793 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 08."
  [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Ruling by the acting president of the "Tribunal Criminal-Revolutionaire" ordering the immediate release from detention of Joseph Lathelise and of Maclou-Claude-Andre Amauri, who had been accused and convicted of "calomniant" (slandering) in speech and print "les representans du peuple" (the representatives of the people in the revolutionary convention). However, becasue Lathelie and Amauri had not acted "sciemment et avec des intentions criminelles et contre-revolutionnaires" (wittingly and with counter-revolutionary intent), they were to be set free on condition that they not be held for other causes."]
- Appointment de Monsieur le Juge du Comte de Benauges, Concernant la Reparation des Chemisn qui traversent et circulent dans l'enceinte dudit Comte. [Judgement/decision/notice of his excellency the judge of the county of Benauges, concerning repair of the roads that traverse and circulate within the boundaries of the said county.], 01/27/1767 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 09."
  [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Joseph Roustaing, Royal Prosecutor and Forester of the County of Benauges (near Bordeaux), complains to the court that the property owners of the county are inflicting great demage on the roads and lanes bordering their individual landholdings: They remove soil from the roads, dig new bordering ditches and fill in old ones, plant rows of trees and hedges on the roads with the consequence that formerly wide roads become narrow lanes, dig pits and create ponds in the roads, and leave piles of wood, stones and manure on them. All this leads to dangers and accidents to travelers and creates impediments to transport of agricultural products. Plaintiff requests that property owners be made to cease their depridations and to restore the roads to former broad and safe conditions. Non compliance to be punished by fines.
  Louis Chardevoine, the Judge, accepts the complaints and issues the present "appointment" (decision/judgement), ordering the inhabitants of the county to cease their depridations, and to restore the roads to their earlier borad (30 feet wide), level (no pits, ditches and ponds), and safe conditions: removing the encroaching trees and hedges, filling in the dangerous pits, and ponds etc., etc. All work to be completed within one month. Non-compliance to be punished by fines or confiscation. The present "appointment" (notice) to be posted throughout the county, in every parish, so that no one may claim ignorance." ]
- Le Marechal de Montrevel, Chevalier des Ordres du Roy. 21 Aoust mil sept cens onze. [Le Marechal de Montrevel, Knight of the King's Orders, 21 August 1711.], 08/21/1711 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 12." [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "The authors have learned that tax collectors will not be able to collect the Royal revenues if they are subject to the reviews and exercises of the Coast-Guard-Militia (a civilian military force that, presumably, must drill and practice on holidays and Sundays) because holidays and Sundays are the most convenient days for collecting the King's revenues. The writers excuse from the aforesaid reviews and exercises one collector from each parish, who will be the tax collector of the previous year, and who will have charge of the tax list [for his parish]. Officers of the Kingdom are forbidden from interfering with the collectors in this matter. Done at Bordeaux, 21 August 1711. Signed Le Marechal de Montrevel, Par Monseigneur Gromel."]
- Baile a Rente pour Madame Petit Contre Ciprien Daniel dermon, 7 Mars 1692. [Rental Property contract for Madame Petit against Ciprien Daniel of Ermon, 7 March 1692.], 07/03/1692 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 17." [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Cyprien Daniel agrees to pay annual rent of 12 livres 7 Sous 2 Deniers to Madame Petit for use of described property, including buildings. Payment to be made each winter on Saint Martin's day."]
- M. Jean Vorse et sa femme Magdalaine Galliot vendent cinq pieces de bois et de terres labourables a M. Pierre de Hodie. 16 Septembre 1644. [Jean Vorse and his wife Magdalaine Galliot sell five sections of woods and of farmable land to Pierre de Hodie. 16 September 1644.] (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 18." [From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Jean Vorse and his wife Magdalaine Galliot certify having sold five sections of woods and farmable land in or near the forest of Montmorency, north of Paris, to Pierre de Hodie. The sections or parceles are described and monies paid are noted."]
- Titre Nouvel pour Madame petit Contre Pierre Gillet fils de Jean Giller et sa femme de Sanoir. le 29 Novembre 1687. (New [property] Title for Madame Petit against Pierre Gilet son of Jean Gilet son of Jean Gillet and his wife of Saunoir, 29 November 1687)., 11/29/1687 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Formerly item numbered: "Schmidt Document 19." From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Pierre gillet and his wife Milinet agree to pay annual rent of twelve pounds to Madame Petit for described property at Ermont, France."
- Contrat de Bail a rente Pour Madame petit de Saint prix contre Louis Daniel of St. Gratich. 18 livres de rente. [Contract of annual rent for Madame petit of Saint prix against Louis Daniel of St. Gratich. 18 pounds rent.], 11/19/1691 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  From preliminary description by Ray Rackley, "Louis Daniel, winegrower of St. Gratich, agrees to pay annual rent of 18 pounds to Madame Petit for use of described property at or near Ermon, France." Handwritten contract. For more information see the preliminary description with item. Formerly folder named "Document 12"